<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle of caution to Friends to take heed of that treacherous spirit that is entred into W.R. and his abettors (as appears in his malicious book, falsly called The Christian-Quaker, &amp;c.) ... : with wholsome advice and counsel, by way of information, that the simple-minded may not be ensnared by the crafts and wiles of Satan through faith fallen antichristian instruments is W.R. and such as are encred into the same malicious spirit with him / C.T.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Christopher, ca. 1615-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20258</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12444077</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12444077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62174</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63474)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62174)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 948:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle of caution to Friends to take heed of that treacherous spirit that is entred into W.R. and his abettors (as appears in his malicious book, falsly called The Christian-Quaker, &amp;c.) ... : with wholsome advice and counsel, by way of information, that the simple-minded may not be ensnared by the crafts and wiles of Satan through faith fallen antichristian instruments is W.R. and such as are encred into the same malicious spirit with him / C.T.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Christopher, ca. 1615-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Bringhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 20.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 20.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709.</term>
               <term>Christian Quaker.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62174:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62174:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE OF Caution to Friends To take heed of that Treacherous Spirit that is entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>W.R.</hi> and his Abettors.</p>
            <p>(As appears in his Malicious Book, falſly called, THE Chriſtian-Quaker, &amp;c.)</p>
            <p>Who under the Profeſſion of Primitive Truth, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying it to the World, and putting Truth's Lambs into their Bears Skins, for the World to worrey, becauſe they have no Power to do it themſelves; who have publiſhed their Wicked Book in <hi>Askelon,</hi> the Fire of their Infamy, and have told it in <hi>Gath,</hi> the Wine-preſs, to preſs out their ſowr Grapes, to ſet the Peoples Teeth on edge againſt the Lambs of God.</p>
            <p>With wholſome Advice and Counſel, by way of Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that the Simple-minded may not be Enſnared by the Crafts and Wiles of Satan, through ſuch Fallen Antichriſtian Inſtruments as <hi>W.R.</hi> and ſuch as are entred into the ſame Malicious Spirit with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>C. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>When the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean Spirit is gone out of a Man, he walketh through dry places, ſeeking Reſt, and finding none. Then he ſaith, I will return into my Houſe, from whence I came out, and when he is come, he findeth it empty, ſwept and garniſhed. Then goeth he, and taketh with himſelf ſeven other Spirits, more Wicked than himſelf, and they enter in, and dwell there; and the laſt State of that man is worſe than the firſt, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 12.43.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for</hi> John Bringhurſt, <hi>at the Sign of the</hi> Book <hi>in</hi> Grace-Church-ſtreet, <hi>near</hi> Cornhill, 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62174:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62174:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe following <hi>Epiſtle of Caution to Friends</hi> being given me to Print, it hath ſeveral times riſe in my Mind, to joyn a ſhort Teſtimony to it, againſt that <hi>Spirit of Diviſion,</hi> and its <hi>Fruits,</hi> by way of <hi>Caution</hi> alſo, that no more may be led aſtray through the ſubtil Wiles and Inſinuations of the Enemy of their Souls, who this day (I am well ſatisfied) makes it his buſineſs, firſt to divide and ſcatter the Sheep from the Fold, and then make a Prey upon them; for thus it was with me for ſome time before I knew of <hi>W.R</hi>'s Book being to be Printed; and I being thus prepared by the Enemy, needed no Arguments to induce me to that which was become ſo natural to me: Wherefore, <hi>Reader,</hi> it riſes in my Heart to Caution all ſuch whom it may concern, to take heed how they hear, leſt they hear amiſs; and how they ſpeak, leſt by their ſpeaking they add ſtrength to thoſe who are already in ſome meaſure led aſtray by the Enemy, to look out at others, when they ſhould look at Home; and not to harbour up anything one againſt another, or againſt the Body, though ſeemingly never ſo ſmall (for <hi>Prejudice</hi> will eat as a <hi>Canker</hi>) nor conſtrue every thing in the worſt ſenſe (as I did) for whoever do, the Hurt will be their own, as it was mine.</p>
            <p>And as to <hi>W.R.</hi>'s Book (which is part of the Fruits of that dividing Spirit (gotten up of late among ſome profeſſing the Truth) entituled, <hi>The Chriſtian-Quaker Diſtinguiſhed from the Apoſtate and Innovator,</hi> &amp;c. it cannot but be expected, that I (who was in ſo large a manner concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as to get it Printed, and afterwards diſowned it) ſhould ſhew ſome Reaſon for my ſo doing, eſpecially ſince it has been ſo noiſed about, both in City &amp; Country by the Propagators and Encouragers thereof, <hi>that a Friend Printed it,</hi> I can do no leſs (in Conſcience to God, and for the clearing his Truth and People) than declare publickly, that I was led thereto by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of my Souls Peace (though I ſaw it not at firſt to be of an Evil Nature) and when I ſaw my Peace was departed, &amp; a weight &amp; lead came upon my Mind, I would have had the peace of the Lord reſtored unto me while I was concerned in the Book; but inſtead thereof, my Trouble was encreaſed, and I ſaw not a way to eſcape the Reward I then was ſenſible would be my Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the Lord was not merciful to me; in which time of Exerciſe, Breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings often went up to the Lord, that if I might find favour in his ſight, he would be pleaſed to ſhow me the way how I ſhould come out of this ſnare &amp; great ſin againſt him, and enjoy his Peace: and the anſwer I in that day received was, <hi>That I was not to expect Peace with the Lord while I perſiſted in the thing which cauſed his Diſpleaſure;</hi> which was the real cauſe of my putting the Book out of my hands before finiſht, the Spirit of the
<pb facs="tcp:62174:3"/>Lord purſuing me from time to time (ſhewing me of what an Evil Tendency it was) till I had rid me of it (though now I ſtand accuſed of <hi>Injuſtice</hi> for ſo doing) and then did the Lord, who had given me Trouble, ſpeak Peace to me, and gave me acceſs (in meaſure) to the Throne of his Grace; for which bleſſed Work, I deſire he may be forever Praiſed and Magnified by and through me whilſt I have a Being here.</p>
            <p>And as to the Publiſhers of this Book of <hi>W.R.</hi> it riſes in my Heart to entreat you all, to ſink down and wait low in the Valley of Humillity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and hearken to hear what Counſel the pure meek Spirit of the Lord (who is the Healer of Breaches) ſaith to you, and yield unto it; for if things were as is pretended in that Book (which I cannot believe) I aver the Lord is againſt any ones diſcovering the Nakedneſs of his Brethren or Fathers in his ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> this day, as in the dayes of <hi>Ham,</hi> or laying ſtumbling Blocks in the way of the weak, as in the dayes of <hi>Balaam,</hi> &amp;c. And let me ask you, What advantage will it bring to the Lord's bleſſed Truth? and what Edification will be reaped by it? and what Honour will it bring to his Name? When I was conſidering the thing (after my Eye began to open) a dread from the Lord ſeized upon me, and the Lord ſhewed me, that it would be a hanious offence committed againſt him, and that I ſhould thereby become Inſtrumental to declare in <hi>Gath</hi> &amp; publiſh in <hi>Askelon</hi> all the dirty villifying ſtuff therein inſerted, which was forbidden to the People of the Lord in the dayes of Old, leſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed in Heart and Ears take occaſion to rejoyce over the People of the Lord: And what will Truths Adverſaries at this day do leſs, think you? Well, <hi>Oh Lord my God, who haſt ſhewed Mercy unto me, if it be thy will, extend thy Mercy unto others, who are yet concerned in the ſpreading and publiſhing of that Book, that they alſo may come to ſee their Error and great Sin againſt thee, and Repent, and ſo come to obtain Mercy at thy Hand before it be too late;</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>And to all ſuch who have, or may have an itching Ear to read that Book, it riſes in my Heart to caution you to forbear ſatisfying your minds therein; for the Enemy may take advantage upon you, thereby to draw out your minds to take every thing for granted thats therein inſerted, &amp; ſo cauſe you to look out at others inſtead of looking after the triming your own Lamps.</p>
            <p>And now having caſed my Spirit of what lay upon me to write, I ſhall at this time conclude with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Cap. <hi>4.</hi> verſ. <hi>1, 2, 3 I therefore—beſeech you, that ye walk worthy of the Vocation wherewith you are called, with all Lowlineſs and Meekneſs, with Long-ſuffering forbearing one another in Love, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Bringhurſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62174:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An</hi> Epiſtle <hi>of</hi> Caution <hi>to</hi> Friends, <hi>to take heed of that Treacherous Spirit that is entred into</hi> W.R. <hi>and his Abettors,</hi> (<hi>as appears in his Malicious Book, falſly called,</hi> The Chriſtian-Quaker, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>)</head>
            <p>HAving ſeen a Book written by <hi>W.R.</hi> I have conſidered the end of his Writing and Printing it, which is to abuſe and miſrepreſent the faithful People of the Lord, who in ſcorn are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as have been faithful to God in their Day and Generation, eminently known to have been ſuch, in this our Day, by being Inſtrumental to turn Hundreds and Thouſands to Righteouſneſs, eſpecially that dear and eminent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God <hi>G.F.</hi> who for his Works ſake in the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus, many do eſteem and honour; and honourable he is to this day, though ſuch as <hi>W.R.</hi> and his Adherents, who (becauſe of Prejudice and Malice) endeavour, what in them lies, to aſperſe him, and abuſe him, and contradict his bleſſed Life, in which he is ſtill made Inſtrumental in the hand of the Lord, to bring forth bleſſed things, for the Service of God and his Truth, from the Oracles of the divine Breath, to the Praiſe of his Name forever.</p>
            <p>The Title of his Book he has Printed, is, <hi>The</hi> CHRISTIAN QUAKER <hi>Diſtinguiſhed from the</hi> APOSTATE <hi>and</hi> IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVATOR.</p>
            <p>Sad it is to conſider the Work of the Enemy, and the Spoil he endeavours to make in the bleſſed Church of God, and Firſt-born, in this our Day; bleſſed be the Lord, and honoured be his Name forever, who has kept a Remnant faithful from Back-ſliding into <hi>Error, Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm,</hi> who retain their Firſt Love, and the Senſe they firſt received in his Eternal Power and Spirit; and by this and through this Senſe, they are able to judge of things that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62174:4"/>differ. And if the Devil ſay (or any whom he has deluded, and led into Blaſphemy) <hi>They are Apoſtatized, or are become Innovators,</hi> and ſo would caſt an Odium upon them, and falſly accuſe them; We know this is the ſame Spirit, though it may be under another Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that alwayes hated the Truth, and deſpiſed the heavenly Counſel, and order of it; and there were ſuch in the Apoſtles dayes, who were unfaithful to God, who abuſed ſuch as kept the Faith, and yet retained the Profeſſion of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in thoſe Primitive Times; yea, <hi>Paul,</hi> that eminent Servant of God, and ſuch as were his faithful Companions in the work of the Goſpel, were not ſpared by them, who loved to reign as Kings without them, and ſet up themſelves as Apoſtles and Miniſters, to lord over Gods Heritage, and to ſeduce the Simple-hearted from the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Faith, and ſo became Inſtruments in the hands of Satan, to bring in the Apoſtacy, which entered by departing from the Power of God, and ſetting up themſelves over the People, by uſurping Authority over their Conſciences, yet under the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith and a good Conſcience, which notwithſtanding they had made Shipwrack of. This curſed Spirit of Satan is now entred into the Heart and Soul of <hi>W.R.</hi> and ſuch of his Abettors as own the <hi>Printing</hi> and <hi>Publiſhing</hi> of his Wicked Book aforeſaid, wherein he has accuſed the faithful Brethren at large, and with a full Mouth, of that which he himſelf is groſly guilty of, that is, <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation.</hi> And for his calling his Book, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker, &amp;c.</hi> it is notoriouſly Blaſphemous, and far unlike the <hi>True Chriſtian Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker;</hi> and let him prove, when at any time any <hi>true Chriſtian Quaker</hi> was Inſtrumental to bring forth ſuch a Work as he has done in his Book, and to gratifie ſuch a People as he has done by <hi>Printing</hi> of it, to the view of the World, as it were to call and invite the Wickedeſt of men, and moſt Malicious againſt Truth, to ſee and behold the <hi>Quakers</hi> Differences, and as much as in him lies, to repreſent the Beſt of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as I may ſo ſay, naked to the view of the Rabble, and the worſt of the Inſtruments of Satan, by them to be Derided, Mocked and Perſecuted, as their Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt was; to render them Bad and Ungodly, to put Weapons into the hands of the Wicked, to War againſt them with, and as much as in them lies, to deſtroy their Lives and Teſtimonies in the Truth of Jeſus.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62174:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Oh! what ſhame is this that W.R. and ſuch as own him in his Writing and Publiſhing of his Book, ſhould call it, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker, &amp;c.</hi> when it is manifeſt to the wiſe in Heart, that it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from a worſe Spirit than that of <hi>Ham,</hi> who uncovered his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Nakedneſs to his Brethren, and therefore was accurſed: Now <hi>Ham,</hi> what he did may be ſaid to be a haſty raſh Action, done on a ſuddain, without Premeditation; but W.R. his Work is far worſe; for he hath long premeditated and laboured to bring forth his Wicked Book in Print, and by ſo doing hath endeavoured to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Nakedneſs of ſuch as once he counted <hi>his Brethren</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> or <hi>Fathers,</hi> whom God hath clothed; but he hath, as it were, endeavoured to preſent them naked to the view of the whole World, by the Publiſhing of his Book, which already has been read and peruſed by <hi>People, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> who are great Enemies to the Truth; and ſo at once has gratified them all, by Printing and Publiſhing his Wicked Book, againſt Gods faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; but that alwayes was the Work of the Enemy in all Ages, to do Wickedly.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Cain</hi> Apoſtatizing from the Faith and Fear of God became Wroth, becauſe God accepted his Brother <hi>Abel</hi>'s Offering, and rejected his, and therefore he turned againſt him and ſlew him. Of this Line of <hi>Cain</hi> is W.R. and his Abettors, and not of the Line of <hi>Abel,</hi> for he envyed not, nor hated his Brother, nor ſought to do him the leaſt Injury, ſo that his Wicked Brother <hi>Cain</hi> ſell upon him without a Juſt cauſe, as now W.R. does in Print, againſt Gods faithful Servants, whoſe Offerings are pure before the Lord, and Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e will clear their Innocency, that in what they do, they ſeek God's Glory, and the Proſperity of his bleſſed Truth. Well, this Blood will cry for Vengeance to God againſt W.R. and his Adherents, as ever the Blood of Righteous <hi>Abel</hi> cryed againſt <hi>Cain,</hi> for Murdering him. <hi>Cain</hi> murdered his <hi>Brother's Body;</hi> but W.R. does what in him lies, to ſhed and let out the <hi>Life of his Brethrens Souls,</hi> by rendring them Dead and Apoſtatized from the Truth that lives forever.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Apoſtates and Innovators, <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and their Company, with the Hundred and Fifty Princes of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, Famous in the Congregation, men of Renown, their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy was ſtrong againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the reaſon was,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62174:5"/>becauſe they departed from the Faith and Fear of God, and ſo loft the ſenſe of his. Love and Preſence, which in ſome meaſure, no doubt, they had known, through the Word of Faith, that was in their Hearts, and might have retained, if they had ſtood in God's Fear, and then they would not have rebelled, and ſo loſt the Senſe of that Accepted State with God, which <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were kept in; nor have Apoſtatized to have contradicted the good Conduct of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> according to God, juſt Appointments; nor have been Innovators under that Diſpenſation, to have endeavoured the <hi>Alteration of the Government eſtabliſhed by the Lord;</hi> nor would they have endeavoured to have <hi>ſet up themſelves over the People, above their true Conditions and Places,</hi> nor to have thruſt out <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> that ſo they might have done according to their own Wills and Luſts, and ſo have been Arbitrary and Tyrannical in their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, without the Power of God, in oppoſition to it; for did not they profeſs <hi>Holyneſs,</hi> and that <hi>all the Congregation was Holy,</hi> and that Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron <hi>took too much upon them, and lift up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord?</hi> Had they not theſe plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Pretences? which were, it ſeems, much taking with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, into which by cunning Deceit and falſe Flattery, they had inſinuated; and ſo the Curſed Preſumption of theſe falſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders, was puniſhed with a Dreadful End: <hi>The Earth opened her Mouth, and ſwallowed them up, und their Houſes, and all the men that appertained unto</hi> Korah, <hi>&amp; all their Goods, they and all that appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, went down alive into the Pit, &amp;c.</hi> A Dreadful End, and juſt from the hand of the Lord.</p>
            <p>So now, let W.R. and his Adherents, dread and fear the living God, who have attempted ſuch manifeſt <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt Gods pure Power, in his bleſſed People, and holy Servants, by rendring them <hi>Apoſtates and Innovators;</hi> for what have they done (to deſerve the Name of <hi>Apoſtates and Innovators</hi>) more than what the Lord has laid upon them, and given them Power to do, in his eternal Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel? What have they brought into the Church of God, or been Inſtrumental in, then to eſtabliſh it in Peace and Unity? And if God hath made uſe of <hi>G. F.</hi> more eſpecially to bring good things from him to his Church, or as his Meſſenger, to be faithful in his Meſſage, to give in that bleſſed <hi>Goſpel Order</hi> and <hi>holy Government of Chriſt,</hi> God hath ſhewn unto him in his holy Spirit, and ſo hath Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed largely in this Work, even beyond many others; why
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62174:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhould he or others, found in ſuch a bleſſed Service, be <hi>Envyed</hi> and <hi>ſpoke Evil againſt,</hi> and be accounted <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators,</hi> and to <hi>take too much upon them?</hi> Remember <hi>Korah</hi> and his company, how they fell, and were ſwallowed up forever with divine Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and no queſtion but <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were tender towards them, to have reclaimed them from their great Preſumption, Pride and Arrogancy, but they would not hear them, but became deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in their Encounter againſt God's Power and true Authority; and therefore God would not ſpare them from Deſtruction, but he was at that time entreated for the poor deluded Congregation; and it is ſaid, they got up from the Tabernacle of <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> &amp;c. and the two Hundred and Fifty Princes, who fell into deſperate Preſumption, and endeavoured to run down <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his Seed from the Prieſthood, theſe were conſumed with Fire, for their Preſumption, in offering Incenſe in oppoſition to Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, under that Diſpenſation, who had eſtabliſhed that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his Seed only.</p>
            <p>So, it is a moſt dangerous thing to oppoſe God's divine Power, and holy Authority, and run againſt and deſpiſe his anointed Ones, whom he has anointed with his holy ſpiritual Oyl, to miniſter unto and ſerve his Church and People, in whatſoever he commands them, who are Miniſters of the Spirit, and not of the Letter.</p>
            <p>They that go from the Power of the Lord are <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators,</hi> and it is they only that would Innovate, or alter the holy Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Power of God, and the Order and Government thereof, becauſe they themſelves are gone from it in their own Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; how can they love the Order, Government and Diſcipline of the Power of God, who love not the Government of it, and to be guided by it in their own Particulars? Thus came in the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> thus came in <hi>Innovations,</hi> and divers <hi>Alterations,</hi> into the Church of God, and a contending for them, that was the ground of ſetting up divers Forms, and Meetings, out of the Power, in which Forms and Meetings Gods Power and Preſence was awanting; theſe the Apoſtle bids turn away from, who had retained the Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but denyed the Power. But the Antient Apoſtles and Elders of the Church of God, kept the Faith, which ſtood in the Power of God; and unto them was the continuance of his Oracles, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Openings, Viſions and Revelations, that in the holy Spirit,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62174:6"/>and Power of the Living God, they might ſerve, obey and worſhip him; theſe when they met together, and had Councils and Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings for the Service and Benefit of the holy Church of God, did wait in the Spirit of Life, to receive from God his Mind and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriy, which they might lay upon the Churches, or ſignifie to them, what was to be done, ſuitable or agreeable to every State, and Time the Church was in, according to her growth and encreate, in the ſpiritual Light and Grace; and therein the Spiritual-minded and Simple-hearted waiting upon the Lord, come to be ſatisfied with the divine Will of God, opened and communicated to them by the Lord, through his Servants and Goſpel Miniſters. And the Simple-hearted <hi>Chriſtians</hi> did not cry out againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> and others of thoſe his Primitive Fellow-Labourers, and call them <hi>Innovators</hi> and <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> or ſuch as were fallen from the Faith, or to <hi>take too much upon them,</hi> but with Love and good Will in the Faith, obſerved the Decrees of the Apoſtles and Elders, and all was ſweet and lovely amongſt them, in ſo doing; and the falſe Apoſtles, falſe Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, falſe Miniſters and Antichriſts, had no place there, ſo long as they kept bleſſedly together, in the Fellowſhip of Gods Eternal Spirit and Power, for then did they ſhine together in the Luſtre and Brightneſs of Gods Wiſdom, and Image of Jeſus Chriſt, mutually ſerving one another in the Love of God, and edifying one another in the moſt holy Faith, and in that ſtate a greater than <hi>Solomon</hi> was known amongſt them, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and the Primitive pure Love of God to poſſeſs their Hearts; ſo that thoſe who kept their Habitations together in the fear of God, and Faith that ſtands in its Eternal Power, were the true Church and Body of the Lord Jeſus, in which was the true Harmony and ſpreading of the heavenly Table, for every Child to receive from God his appointed Food and Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, to eat the Fleſh and drink the Blood of the Lord Jeſus, and diſcern the Lord's Body, in true Temperance, Sobriety and Moderation in Chriſt Jeſus, where there is neither Damnation nor Condemnation, but a true real Growth, and Encreaſing with the Encreaſe of God, unto a true and ſubſtantial Man in Chriſt Jeſus; ſuch flouriſhed in their Day and Time, Age and Generation, and are upon record a good favour to God and his faithful People, who are made Partakers of the ſame bleſſed and heavenly Life with them: Of this Line and Spiritual Generation, are ſuch now as live
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62174:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the true reverend fear of God, and in his Power, and are ſhod with the Preparation of the Goſpel of Peace, and ſo are ſafe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and continued in the Boſom, and under the ſhadow of a moſt tender Father, mindful of his Mercies, and the Continuance of his Kindneſs, who has kept them hitherto over all Apoſtates, and Prophane, to the praiſe of his everlaſting Name, who is God over all bleſſed for evermore.</p>
            <p>But there were then, and are ſuch now, as are Apoſtatized, and gone from the Power of God, and the Sence of thoſe who are kept in it, (yet notwithſtanding they may in words profeſs the Power, and Truth as at firſt appeared) and that is the ground of their Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and Weakneſs of underſtanding, and uncapableneſs to know and diſcern what is of God, and what is of the Enemy, who are his true and faithful Servants and People, who ſtill have kept their Habitations in the Truth; and who are Apoſtatized, and would bring in Innovations, in contradiction to the will of God and his heavenly Power amongſt his People, and are become twice dead, plucked up by the Roots, and thorow Perverſneſs, Peeviſhneſs, and Croſs-ſpiritedneſs, enter into the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and Spirit of <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> and his Company, of which number and ſort is <hi>W. R.</hi> and his Adherents, that is, ſuch as own him in the <hi>Writing, Printing</hi> and <hi>Publiſhing</hi> his Book, falſly called, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But though he and others, may harden themſelves againſt good Admonition to their Deſtruction (except they Repent) and an Earthly Spirit may ſwallow them up, as outwardly the Earth open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſwallowed up <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, and alſo the <hi>fifty intruding and rebelling Princes,</hi> and <hi>men of Renown</hi> (ſo called) were conſumed with the Fire of the Lord; Yet I hope the Lord will be merciful to many, who yet ſee not through their Deceit, yet may be ſomewhat intangled by them, and miſ-led through their falſe and inſinnuating-ſpiritedneſs, yet are not hardned to Perdition; I hope God will deliver ſuch in due time, who in their Hearts ſingly and nakedly cry to him, for a true De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſion, in matters wherein they have not yet a clear underſtanding and eſtabliſhed Judgment.</p>
            <p>Do not <hi>W. R.</hi> and his Adherents yet underſtand the way of the wicked Spirit, whither it leads, and how it has led many into an evil condition, to forſake the living God, and his Power, and ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62174:7"/>became Grand Oppoſers of the ſame Heavenly Power, and Croſs of Jeſus; and ſome at laſt have been ſo fool-hardy, to ſplit and break themſelves in pieces forever, by <hi>Printing</hi> and <hi>Publiſhing</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, out of Envy and Malice, as <hi>W. R.</hi> has done, as at large may be ſeen in his Book, to render us <hi>degenerated, gone from our firſt Principles and Power of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how have ſuch proſpered! Do they not remember the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of many in <hi>J. N.</hi> his time, and what Scandal they brought on Truth in that day, by departing from the Power of God, to the wounding of their own Souls, and the Souls of many tender-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Friends and Brethren? and would we not then have ſaved them with our tender Advice? but ſome periſhed and became perfectly obſtinate, and ran out from the Truth, and never more returned into it, that we know of; And did not <hi>R. R.</hi> and ſome others, who became hardned in Prejudice, <hi>Write</hi> and <hi>Print</hi> againſt us, who kept our Habitations in the Truth, and eſpecially moſt maliciouſly againſt that dear Servant of the Living God <hi>G. F.</hi> who kept his Habitation and Authority in the living Truth, over all thoſe unclean Spirits who then troubled the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>But that Day paſſed over, and we ſaw through it and over it; and they who then returned not through Judgment, do not ſo much as retain the <hi>Profeſſion of Truth;</hi> Did not they then ſay, <hi>We were gone from the Power and were Apoſtatized, and were ſetting up Forms and preaching to the People like Prieſts, &amp;c.</hi> But ſaid, they themſelves were entring into a further Diſpenſation of Joy, and Liberty, and Love; but that feigned love turned into Envy, and at laſt it proved they were gone from the Power of God into their own Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which would not keep them from doing things unſeemly, and ſo became treacherous to their own Souls, and to the Truth of God, and ſome periſhed in their Gain-ſayings.</p>
            <p>And one <hi>R. S.</hi> a <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Man, when he turned from the Truth into Prejudice againſt Good Advice and Order; have they not heard how he Apoſtatized, and had his Children ſprinkled by the Prieſt, and ſo became Treacherous and falſe to God, his People, and his own Soul, and then at laſt he did as <hi>W. R.</hi> and his Adherents have now done, who own the Printing and Publiſhing his wicked Book, called, the <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, then at laſt he maliciouſly Printed, to revile and reproach the Truth, and the Poſſeſſors of it;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62174:7"/>for when ſuch as <hi>W. R.</hi> and his Abettors have hardned their Hearts againſt good Admonition, until they have fallen into open oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the Power of God, his faithful. Servants and bleſſed People, who keep the Truth, then they have come to be ſhameleſs, and to enter into the ſame <hi>Oppoſing, Malicious, Contradicting Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> with the envious Prieſts and Profeſſors, and ſo have become blind Leaders of the Blind, and they who have been ſuch Leaders, and who have been led by them, have fallen into the Ditch, and Periſhed in their Gain-ſaying, except they have found a place for Repentance.</p>
            <p>And many others, when they have been hardned in Rebellion and Wickedneſs againſt the Truth and the Poſſeſſors of it, who have kept their Habitations in it, maliciouſly as now <hi>W. R.</hi> at laſt hath done, have Printed and Publiſhed, to the view of the World, which when they have appeared ſo wicked, it hath been a manifeſt fign of their Deſtruction and Death, as to Truth, as <hi>J. Penniman, J. B.</hi> and others; and ſo now <hi>W. R.</hi> at laſt Printing and Publiſhing his wicked malicious Book, it is a manifeſt token of his Deſtruction as to Truth, and the ruin and undoing of his Soul forever, and the Souls of all, who in this Spiritedneſs adhere to him, and own the Printing and Publiſhing of his Book, falſly called, the <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> &amp;c. except they Repent; And this from God I have received concerning his and their ſtate at preſent, and Pray, that if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, he and they all who unit with him in this work of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, may find a place of Repentance; for their caſe is miſerable, and Wo and Miſery will be their portion forever, except they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; for the God of Heaven is angry with them, and it will break forth upon them, and they ſhall know that he is the Living God with his People, that they may ſtand and be eſtabliſhed by him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and that neither <hi>W. R.</hi> nor his Adherents will be able to pull them down, even ſuch whom he hath ſo vilified and abuſed in his Book, and eſpecially that dear Servant of God <hi>G. F.</hi> whom he hath ſo baſely beſpattered in his Book, and Printed and Publiſhed this to the World, as I may ſay, to put ſuch a monſtrous ſhape upon him, as that the very worſt of men may fall upon him. Is this <hi>Love?</hi> nay, it is <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and monſtrous <hi>Iniquity;</hi> and the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of <hi>W. R.</hi> and his Adherents, which they muſt bear for theſe things, will be too heavy for them; and Truth will prevail over all,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62174:8"/>and God will put his Beauty and Comlineſs ſtill more and more upon ſuch as dear <hi>G. F.</hi> and others who are faithful to the living God, and a thorow Deciſſion will come, that in the end, the Simple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, that fear the Lord in their Hearts, may be undeceived of the falſe Coverings of <hi>W. R.</hi> and his Abettors, and then they will be eaſily ſeen and diſcerned, as they are in their Nature, to the view of every Upright-hearted Friend that loves the Truth; and ſo their rank will be found to be the ſame with <hi>R. S. J. Penniman, R. R.</hi> and the reſt afore-mentioned, who went the ſame way, and at laſt grew wicked in Printing and Publiſhing, as <hi>W. R.</hi> hath now done.</p>
            <p>And whereas ſome profeſſing Truth have been offended with <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> as now eſtabliſhed amongſt us by the Power of God, and the Practices of ſuch Meetings, calling them <hi>Innovations,</hi> (viz.) <hi>That it is a bringing in of new things into the Church, or altering the ſtate of it, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto this I Anſwer; That <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Good Order</hi> is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be eſtabliſhed in every Family, much more in the Church of God, that every Member of the true Church may know its Place and Service in the Body, fitted thereunto by the Power of God; then will it fall in naturally and in courſe, that every Member will know its Office, and whereunto it is called, with the heavenly Call of Chriſt Jeſus, and theſe are they that take their Poſſeſſions in the Life, Power, and Wiſdom of God, and are fit to do ſervice in the Church, and of ſuch Members is, and ought to be, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> who reverence and fear the Living God, and have a care of his Service, and that all that profeſs Truth, and that are turned to it, may be preſerved in it, then ſuch faithful Members, and ſavoury ſanctified Ones, whether men or women, when they meet together in their Meetings, meet with the Lord in the midſt of them, and his pure Wiſdom and Power to guide them in that they are called unto, as they faithfully and truly wait upon him in ſuch Meetings; ſo the Work is the Lord's they are about, and thoſe that are faithful unto God, and Eye his Power, and ſeek his Glory in the courſe of their Lives, will not fail to do the ſame in theſe Meetings, and as ſo, then let the Wiſe in Heart judge, <hi>Whether this be not the Way of God, for the eſtabliſhment of Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Government in his Church, that all may be kept ſweet and ſavoury in his Houſe, to his Praiſe forever.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62174:8"/>
            <p>And how this can be called <hi>Innovation,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtatizing into Forms,</hi> is certainly Monſtrous, and great Ignorance, where the Power of God is kept unto; for no other Meetings, we do affirm in Gods Preſence, we account right, but as they are <hi>Conſtituted in the Power God,</hi> and <hi>kept in it;</hi> and this we affirm to have been the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Practice, ſo long as they kept to the Power; but when there is a going from the Power, and that comes to be loſt, as to them, then all Meetings are alike, to ſuch; and ſo came in the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Innovations,</hi> after the Primitive pure Times, and then the Key of knowledge came to be loſt, and Antichriſtian Formality to be ſet up, and gradually many ſtrange Ceremonies and ſuperſtitious Things to be obſerved; and that was all wrong, and the Order of God's Power and Truth was awanting in thoſe times, as to the true Church and the true Government of it, becauſe their Churches, ſo called, were ſaid to be <hi>viſible Churches,</hi> conſiſting of <hi>Nations</hi> or <hi>Pariſhes,</hi> &amp;c. But the true Church was inviſible, to the Carnal-minded Ones, and ſuch as did not fear the Lord, nor worſhip him in Spirit and Truth; though God had his Witneſſes in the darkeſt times of Ignorance, <hi>Popery</hi> and Superſtition, which had ſpread over all, and Nations had drunk the Whores Cup of filthy Abominations, yet ſome Witneſſes were raiſed up by the Lord, to bear witneſs againſt the Wickedneſs and Abomination of thoſe times.</p>
            <p>Now the true Church of God, which is coming to appear out of her Wilderneſs ſtate, begins to flouriſh, and to become as a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den watered and pruned by the pure Power of God, and for this end God in our D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y has raiſed up many Witneſſes, bleſſed be his Name forever, and they are at work in his Garden, the Heavenly Plantation of his own Hand, and ſeek his Glory in all things.</p>
            <p>And now, the Heavenly Wiſdom ſees meet, to give ſorth again <hi>true Goſpel-Order</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> as in the Church of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtacy entred, and makes choice of ſuch as are capable in this Work, and Spiritual-minded; and when they come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they can rejoyce in the enjoyment of God's preſence with them; and the Holy Order of the Goſpel is committed to ſuch, whether Men or Women: And whether in theſe Meetings, or in other Meeting, any thing be ſaid or done thorow Infirmity, or want of a good Underſtanding in ſome, who may come to ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62174:9"/>Meetings, that does not overthrow the conſtitution of any Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the Power of God hath ſet up, and is the Authority of; but the Endeavour is and ought to be, <hi>that there may be a growth, in the Truth in all theſe things, by ſuch as are faithful, untill the Houſe of God be eſtabliſhed in its Glory, and God's heavenly Wiſdom and Power ſhine through all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the Foundation of <hi>good Meetings,</hi> and <hi>good Order</hi> in the Church of God, is truly laid amongſt us by the Lord; and it is he that lays thoſe good things upon us, which we do in our Men and Womens Meetings, in relation to <hi>good Order</hi> in <hi>Marriages:</hi> and many other neceſſary things, which are done in ſuch Meetings bring honour to God; for the ſtate of the Churches is enquired into, <hi>that every true Neceſſity may be anſwered;</hi> and, if poſſible, <hi>every diſorderly thing may be ſeparated, and done away; and the living innocent-hearted Ones may be encouraged in their Obedience and Faithfulneſs to God, helped and aſſiſted in their Sufferings; and the Diſobedient and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithful may be exhorted to Obedience, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in things relating to their Conditions; that all Looſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty may be kept out of the Church of God, and Youth or Young People, whether Male or Female, may not be encouraged to a Looſe Liberty, in any thing, but may be truly ſubject to the Power of God, and the Order of it in his Church, that all may be kept pure and clean.</hi> And what God hath joyned together, let no man or men put aſſunder or divide, in crying down <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> ſome rude, ungodly-ſpirited Ones calling them an <hi>Idol</hi> and an <hi>Image,</hi> and preſenting <hi>Marriage</hi> before them, they call, <hi>Dancing about an Idol,</hi> and ſuch filthy and unſavoury ſtuff as that is, is caſt out from the unclean Spirit of foul and unſanctified minds: and ſome ſay, <hi>They deny Womens Meetings, Root and Brauch,</hi> and much more ſuch Unſavourineſs, and Abuſive Language, proceeds from them, who would be <hi>ſticklers in the Church of God,</hi> and would <hi>reign as Kings without their faithful Brethren,</hi> to ſet up themſelves in an abuſive, preſumptuons, proud, ſcornful and diſdainful Spirit.</p>
            <p>And theſe are ſuch as are <hi>Sticklers</hi> and <hi>Promoters</hi> of <hi>W.R's</hi> Printed Book aforementioned, and ſome ſuch are his Factors in ſelling them for him: though <hi>J. S.</hi> their great Friend and Elder, ſayes, <hi>He is not againſt Womens Meetings.</hi> So ſee what <hi>confuſion</hi> they are in.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62174:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now faithful Womens Meetings are bleſſed of God, and we are living Witneſſes of God's heavenly preſence with them; and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will be to thoſe who endeavour to ſcatter them, and pull down the Services which they are appointed unto; better they had never been, Born, except they Repent; and that which is their great Confirmation againſt all the Oppoſition of the wicked Spirited, that riſe up againſt them, is the feeling of God's bleſſed heavenly Power and Preſence in the midſt of them, which is a manifeſt ſign of God's accepting of them in their coming together, to wait upon him, and preſent themſelves before him, to do that Work and Service in his Fear and Dread which they are appointed to do.</p>
            <p>So, let all ſlanderous Tongues forever be ſilent, in calling ſuch Meetings, or the Services performed in them, in the good Order of Truth and Goſpel Power, <hi>Innovations</hi> and <hi>Apoſtatizing from the Truth,</hi> and a <hi>ſetting up empty Forms, Images and Idols;</hi> but God's Power in all Ages hath had its <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Manner of Appearance,</hi> and who ſhall limit it, and ſay, <hi>Thus far ſhall it bring forth, and no farther?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, I charge every one, in the fear of God, to take heed of kicking againſt the Pricks, and turning againſt any thing the Power of God brings forth, to be done and obſerved; and that all be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Services one of another, which God may appoint unto, that the Spirit of God may not be quenched in any, or that either Men or Women be diſcouraged from going on in the Work of the Meetings, in what the Lord may have for them to do; but rather let us encourage them, as much as in us lies, that ſo without Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, the heavenly Power of the living God, may ſtill have its Paſſage through Men and Women, Male and Female, Young or Old, both in their Meetings, and out of Meetings: and let all take heed of a croſs Cankered Spirit, which through Prejudice is ready to carp at every thing that good and honeſt Friends do in their Meetings, and pleaſed with little or nothing; for they that are entred into that Spirit, are become Fighters againſt God in a large Meaſure, and Diſturbers of the Church's Peace.</p>
            <p>But ſome may object, <hi>Theſe things were not in the Beginning, when Truth broke forth amongſt us, but are Innovations brought in ſince, and are of a dangerous Conſequence, to the eſtabliſhing and ſetting up Forms, and bringing in the Apoſtacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62174:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I Anſwer;</hi> What was in the beginning, we very well know, and far better than many do who talk ſo much of it; We know the Power of God was in the Beginning, and raiſed up many to Life, who had been dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, that was its firſt Works, and the effects of it was Righteouſneſs; and ſo the Lord is raiſing, and hath raiſed up a People that they may ſerve him, and may be his in this Day wherein he is making up his Jewels; and theſe bleſſed Jewels are not made up at once, but through the divers Operations and Miniſtrations of his Power; and before there was a People raiſed, there was no occaſion for <hi>Men and Womens Meetings;</hi> but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees Truth encreaſed, and many were raiſed; and afterwards ſome can out into Scandalous and Diſorderly Practices, in Marrying, and in Diſorderly Living, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And alſo, beſides theſe things, other true Neceſſities called for Men and Womens Meetings to be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed gradually, and ſettled, as now is, by the Power of God; But ſome, who in the beginning, as was in the Apoſtles dayes, may have known the breaking forth of the Power of God, and divers Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of it, and in that day had good deſires raiſed up to perſevere in the way of his Judgments, until Judgment ſhould be brought forth to Victory, and ſo begun in the Spirit, and ſerved God in what he called them unto, as they were faithful; yet notwithſtanding this, though Truth might be precious to ſuch then, and alwayes is to every one that keeps in it, and wait to know the way of it, in ſubmitting their Will to the Will of God, that his divine Wiſdom and heavenly Spirit may ſtill guide them, and direct them, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we know ſome have ſtept out of the Simplicity of Gods Truth, and have entred into their own Reaſonings, and dark Wiſdom, and bruitiſh Knowledge, and ſo have ſtumbled at what God hath, and now is bringing forth concerning our <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Womens Meetings</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and the like, and the Services of ſuch Meetings, appointed by the Power of God; and ſo ſeeing the Proſperity of ſuch Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and Services, they are entred into a fretting, peeviſh-ſpirited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt ſuch things, and ſo gradually hardning, through ſetting up their own Reaſons in their own Wills, and leaning to their own Underſtandings, have grown into ſuch a Confidence, either againſt ſuch Meetings, or ſome of the good Services of them, that at laſt they have become ſo prejudiced, that that which at firſt ſeemed to be but as a little <hi>Fault-finding, or Jealouſie in their Minds,</hi> is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62174:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>come to be grown into a Mountain of Oppoſition, and for want of a perſeverance, and enduring to the end in that Spirit in which they begun well, ſome have fallen, and are falling from the Power of God, and from the Senſe of their Elders and Brethren in the Truth, and have run out againſt them, and ſome at laſt have Printed and Publiſhed, as now W. R. hath done, who could not abide ſound Life and Doctrine. And therefore, I pray and beſeech God, that none may fall into this Snare, who are yet preſerved out of it but that they may be preſerved ſimple before the Lord, as in the beginning, when the Lords Power broke forth in them, and melted their Hearts into Tenderneſs, &amp; ſo will God bleſs them, and ſtill keep them in the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of his Truth, and honour them, that they may witneſs the Election to obtain, and never to be deceived by falſe Gloſſes and fair Pretences, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I remember, formerly God preparatively was at Work, in order to reveal that Myſtery, which had been hid from Ages and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſince the Apoſtles dayes; and ſome were convinced of Sin, and had ſights of good things to come, and in ſome meaſure came to be ſeparated from the Sins of the Times, and they did ſee a neceſſity of ſeparating from the groſs Multitude in their Worſhips, and ſo did deſire to ſeek after God, and to wait upon him, and the Lord touched them ſometimes, and made them ſenſible of the neceſſity of ſtill preſſing forwards after the enquiry of better things than they then were made Partakers of; and ſome of theſe, who after this continued ſimple, and had their Eye to the Lord, and were ſo pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued with Judgment for Iniquity, that they could not fully give up the Reigns to it, and ſo were under the Spirit of Judgment and Bondage, or at Times, as I may ſay, great Fears; theſe thus tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling on in their Spirits, and being kept in this Exerciſe, when the Power of the Lord broke forth in our Nation, it met with many ſuch, and they received the Truth with us, in the Love of it, and came to witneſs the Operation of it, and are preſerved in it, &amp; will be ſorever, as ſtill they preſs forwards in their true Enquiry to diſcern &amp; know the Way of God's Spirit, and the Products of his holy Power.</p>
            <p>Now there were ſome, who, as aforeſaid, were touched and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed with the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in their own Conſciences, and for a time continued ſeeking after a farther Condition, than that of living in Sin, under the Notion &amp; Profeſſion of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> but after
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62174:11"/>a time, going from the Simplicity of Innotent Enquiry after the Lord, and his Power and Goſpel, they became <hi>Wiſe in Notions,</hi> and aſpired to <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> with the <hi>Fragments of Old, Broken and Weak Experiences,</hi> together with the Addition of their <hi>own Comprehenſions, Wit and Invention,</hi> and ſo became Wiſe in their own Conceits, and ſo fell back into the low Worldly Things, in a Worldly Spirit, &amp; a Self-Righteous, and a Phariſaical State: Now theſe, when the Truth and Doctrine of the Light of Jeſus, in the Evidence of God's mighty Power, came to be publiſhed, as the Phariſees did, ſo they did, even rebel againſt it, and as bad as the common Prieſts, became our bitter Enemies under ſpecious and fair guilded Pretences, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now, this I relate as a Caution to thoſe now who have received the Truth in the Love and Simplicity of it, that they may take heed and keep to it in Simplicity, that their Underſtandings may be kept open, and their Hearts chaſte and pure to Chriſt and God, then will they in the Faith ſtill follow on to know, that at laſt they may come to be ſo eſtabliſhed, that the Devil can have Power no more to deceive them with all his Gloſſes and fair Pretences; but they who are Careleſs, and keep not to the Simplicity of Truth, as it is in Jeſus, but let out their Minds into a falſe Liberty, and in their Hearts are diſobedient to God, though they have known the Power of God in ſome meaſure, and once were deſirous to know his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet notwithſtanding, going from the Power and Croſs of Jeſus, into a falſe Liberty of uſhering their own Self-Wills and Wits in Truth's Matters, endeavouring to comprehend the Simplicity of the Way of God's Spirit, and the Products of his heavenly Power, by leaning and truſting to their own Underſtandings, though otherwiſe they may appear in a Self-Righteouſneſs, with fair Pretences and Gloſſes, to deceive the Hearts of the Simple, yet for all this God will find them out; and this is too much the Condition of W. R. and his Adherents; who, had they kept to the Simplicity of the Government of the pure and chaſte Power of God, in their own Particulars, they would not have grown ſo Fool-hardy as to be ſeen Publiſhing and Patronizing ſuch a Treacherous Wicked Book, as that falſly called, <hi>The Chriſtian-Quaker, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now one thing more I have to ſay at this time, in relation to ſuch tender ſimple-hearted Friends, as may be ready to ſtumble at the appointing of <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Womens Meetings, fearing leſt it ſhould
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62174:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>bring in Formality, and uſher in an Apoſtacy;</hi> and ſome are too ready, to ſtrengthen ſuch a jealouſie in them, by telling them, <hi>Now you ſee the Apoſtacy is coming in, for ſo it came in, in the Primitive Times, by ſetting up Councils, and Meetings, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which <hi>I Anſwer;</hi> Though ſome have in this day been found too much promoting ſuch falſe Doctrine amongſt ſimple People, to make them evil affected with our bleſſed Meetings, in the Power of Chriſt, yet I ſay, the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> firſt came in by <hi>departing from the Power of God,</hi> and then their <hi>Meetings</hi> were <hi>empty Forms,</hi> without the Power, and they fell into Confuſion, and Diſorder, and many Sects, and divers falſe Opinions, and ſo all along to our day, the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> hath continued amongſt all, who have not come to the true Faith that ſtands in the Power; and this we clearly came to ſee, when we were convinced of Gods holy Truth, and to declare (as we ſtill do, and I hope ever ſhall) againſt all ſuch formal Worſhips, as are ſet up by the Will and Wit of man; but had they ſtood in Gods Counſel, they would have known the Heavenly Worſhip in Spirit and Truth, and been one with us in this day, but their Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings being out of the Power, is the Ground we cannot own them, and therefore the Primitive Meetings, before the Apoſtacy came in, now come to be reſtored amongſt us, and the heavenly Power of Jeſus to be the Author of them, and not a worldly Pope or Biſhop, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo let none be jealous at our <hi>appointing Meetings</hi> for Gods Work and Service in his holy Truth, becauſe they may be very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the Antichriſtian Meetings all abroad, where the Meeters and Aſſemblers together, band together againſt Gods holy Truth, and the Poſſeſſors of it.</p>
            <p>And let none be jealous, <hi>That we have not the ſame Care of God's Honour and Glory, that we had when the Truth broke firſt out amongſt as;</hi> but rather believe, that our <hi>Godly Care</hi> is encreaſed, and doth ſtill encreaſe, and that we are ſtill of God, neither dare nor can appoint or ſet up any thing againſt the Truth, but for the Service of it, as the Lord moves us, and that the Power of the Lord may ſtill be the Authority and Ground of all our Meetings, and all Friends may encourage one another in that which is Virtuous, Holy, Clean and Comely, to the Praiſe of the Everlaſting, and only Wiſe God, who lives and reigns forever.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62174:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And this in pure Love was upon my Spirit to write, as a Caution to Honeſt-hearted Friends, to take heed of that Spirit of W. R. and his Abettors, and of J. S. and J. W. who ſhelter under it, who will not be ſeen to Print themſelves, but have afforded W. R. mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to fill up his Book with, who is ſo Imperious and Malicious, that it ſeems he tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> little heed what he ſaith or doth; Thus have they and their Adherents endeavoured to betray us to the World, <hi>Judas</hi>-like, and like all others who have been found in the ſame Evil and Ungodly Work with them.</p>
            <p>And I truly deſire they may come to ſee what Maſter they ſerve, and whoſe Work they are doing, and Repent, and call in and judge all their Evil Work, which they have Printed and ſpread abroad, to defile Simple and Ignorant Minds with; for the Wiſe in Heart ſee both it and them, and are taught how to avoid it all.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. Taylor.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>the 12th of the 3d Moneth, 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 3. line 15. dele <hi>who.</hi> P. 6. l. 36. dele <hi>give in</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>John Bringhurſt,</hi> viz.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The Life of Chriſt magnified in his Miniſter; Or, certain Teſtimonies thereof, relating to his Faithful Servant</hi> GILES BARNARDISTON, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Price 3 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Epiſtle of</hi> PAUL <hi>to the</hi> LAODICEANS; Price <hi>One half Penny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An</hi> EPISTLE <hi>of Caution to</hi> FRIENDS, <hi>to take heed of that Treacher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirit that is entred into</hi> W. R. <hi>and his Abettors, as appears in his Malicious Book, falſly called,</hi> The Chriſtian Quaker, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Price <hi>Three half Pence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62174:12"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
